<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A new booke, intituled, I am for you all, complexions castle as well in the time of the pestilence, as other times, out of the which you may learne your complexion, your disease incident to the same, and the remedies for the same. Published by Iames Manning, minister of the word.</title>
            <title>I am for you all, complexions castle</title>
            <author>Manning, James, minister at Wellingborough.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1604</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 104 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06820</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17257</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109784</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845429</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845429</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10326</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06820)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10326)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 812:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A new booke, intituled, I am for you all, complexions castle as well in the time of the pestilence, as other times, out of the which you may learne your complexion, your disease incident to the same, and the remedies for the same. Published by Iames Manning, minister of the word.</title>
                  <title>I am for you all, complexions castle</title>
                  <author>Manning, James, minister at Wellingborough.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Legat, printer to the Vniuersitie of Cambridge. 1604. And are to be sold at the signe of the Crowne in Pauls Church-yard [, London] by Simon Waterson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Cambridge] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1604]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: I am for you all, complexions castle.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hygiene --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Medicine --  Formulae, receipts, prescriptions --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:10326:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10326:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A NEW BOOKE, intituled, <hi>I am for you all, Complexions
caſtle:</hi> as well in the time of the peſtilence, as <hi>other times, out
of the which you may learne your</hi> complexion, your diſeaſe incident to
<hi>the ſame, and the remedies for</hi> the ſame.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed by IAMES MANNING, <hi>miniſter of the word.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Morbus cedat medico, arti nuſquam mors.</q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Cambridge University Press</figDesc>
               <q>HINC LVCEM ET POCVLA SACRA ALMA MATER CANTA<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>BRIGIA</q>
            </figure>
            <p>PRINTED BY IOHN LEGAT, PRIN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the Vniuerſitie of
<hi>Cambridge.</hi> 1604.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And are to be ſold at the ſigne of the Crowne in Pauls
Church-yard by</hi> Simon Waterſon.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:10326:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10326:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Sir <hi>Thomas Bennet,</hi> Lord Major
of the citie of London.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Heras it is the order of the moſt, to dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate vnto the
beſt deſeruer, as well in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of worthines of the one, as office and
dutie of the other, I deeme me not to dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate, in dedicating vnto your L.
this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, which is dimmed for want of time, wherein more acuitie might
haue increaſed, yet perfectly ſeeing the way wherein to wait attendance,
for your L. vſe and ſeruice: the readier for that your L. is placed a
prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour ouer our worthieſt and moſt famous place of protection, whoſe
wings beeing but bedewed with falſe report of peſtilence, no ſmall ſort
doe ſauour of diſtreſſe, there, and els where: but bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by death
diſplumed of many, and diſpoſſeſſed of more by daily departure, may
iuſtly poſſeſſe all with griefe, and deſire to releeue, to ſee
the citie in griefe, induring ſeparation daily, whereas vnitie ſhould be
howerly: the rather, for that your L. hath not beene abſent, but with your
brethren carefully buſied, in comforting, releeuing, and preuenting, which
ought to be a ioy and comfort for all, to ſee the diſtreſſed haue ſo
readie a keye, not onely to ſhut vp, and ſecure from purſuing
peſtilence, but to let out at libertie without waſt of the afflicteds
wealth. Of which ioy I taking part, haue ioyfully imparted, this little labour,
which I ſhall with more ioy in better manner, indeuour to polliſh and
finiſh, and with moſt ioy of all bold to dedicate vnto your L. if this may
mooue your Honour, to limit the ſame to paſſe in open way, where the
moſt may accompanie the benefit therein: which I humbly commend vnto your L.
as a better, beſeeching the beſt of all, to comfort your Honourable
eſtate with increaſe and continuance of happines and heauenly bliſſe.
And ſo ceaſing your further trouble, J humbly take my leaue.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From Wellingborough in Northamptonſhire. 
<date>Septem. <hi>1. 1604.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline> 
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your L. in his beſt indeuours to command,</hi> Iames
Manning.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:10326:3"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>HAuing conſidered the careles regard of many concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the
health of themſelues, and others, and the great neceſſitie in this
greiuous viſitation: I could not but inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to counſell, and to releeue
by this poore pamphlet, poore in regard of plaineneſſe, reſpecting the
plainer ſort, whoſe welcome ſhall admoniſh wearineſſe to be
wanting, when I ſhall heareafter in better ſort be buſied, in finiſhing
this ſlender and ſhort labour, poſted forward to helpe, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though not to
finiſh ſuch a needfull worke, which I leaue to the long deuiſed, and
learned lines of others, extant, or to come, whome I neuer minded to rob of any
rightes, neither purpoſed to preuent by publiſhing of this: but as all
could not be free maſons, goldſmithes, and principall workmen at the
building of the temple, for then few of them ſhould haue liued, to haue
finiſhed their worke, or haue ſeene the vſe thereof, and for that the
commaundement, neceſſitie, and the godly end thereof, did mooue the meaner
ſort, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they brought timber, ſtone, morter, rubbiſh, and
neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie matter for the workemen, to make choiſe of: So in my well
wiſhing to helpe, I could not combine with content, to take eaſe, and be
abſent from building, hauing no more gor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous meanes, or curious matter, but
againſt feare to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend Zoilus, Theon, and the curious crew, haue poſted
this pamphlet, to paſſe for a welcome, to ſo many, as ſhall here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
feele themſelues better mooued, or any waies amended. In hope whereof I
commend thee with my prayers to the phyſitian of ſoule and body.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:10326:3"/>
            <head>The Contents of this booke.</head>
            <list>
               <item>MAn is not to ſuffer bad humors in himſelfe nor others.
<hi>Chap. 1, 2, 3. 4.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How the peſtilent aire is cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, how it worketh. <hi>c.
5. 6. 7</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Signes ſhewing the aire to be infected in ſubſtance, in
qualitie, in ſubſtance and qualitie. <hi>c. 8, 9, 11.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Signes ſhewing the aire to be infected in qualitie the next
yeare following. <hi>c. 10.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Signes ſhewing if the putre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction proceedeth from the
places vpon the earth or from within the earth. <hi>c. 12.13.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>From whence the infection is now. <hi>c. 14.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The infection is more dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at the noſtrells
then at the mouth. <hi>c. 15.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The putrified aire cannot paſſe to the heart by the
organes of ſmelling ſo ſpeedilie as in moſt creatures. <hi>c.
16.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Which of the virulent quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in the aire is apteſt to
be taken and to deſtooy. <hi>c. 17.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The ſanguin complexion is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt to take the infection,
the time when. <hi>c. 18, 19. 20.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Signes to knowe the ſanguin complexion. <hi>c.
21.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Signes to knowe if the blood in the ſanguin or other
com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion be infected. <hi>c. 22.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Meanes to clenſe the blood in this complexion. <hi>c. 23,
24, 25. 26.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Meanes to make the ſanguin complexion leſſe apt to take
it hauing clenſed the blood. <hi>c. 27. 28.</hi> and to know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they
haue taken it. <hi>c. 28.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The pome for this complexion to ſmell vpon and to vſe in
the time of peſtilence. <hi>c. 29.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The water for this complexion to vſe for their houſes and
clothes. <hi>c. 30.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The perfume for this complex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion. <hi>c. 31.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The pilles for this complexion. <hi>c. 32.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Meanes what to doe if this complexio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuſpect they haue
taken it. <hi>c. 34.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Things good to be vſed by this complexion in the time of
peſtilence. <hi>c. 33. 35, 36, 37.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Things ill for this complexion in the time of peſtilence.
c. <hi>38.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Hearbes good for this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion in the time of pesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence.
<hi>c. 39.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Things not conuenient for the ſanguine complexion. <hi>c.
40.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10326:4"/>Thinges conuenient. <hi>c. 41.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What fruites are ſeldome to be vſed of this complexion in
the time of peſtilence. c. <hi>42. 43.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What fruites and ſeedes are good for the liuer in this
complexion. <hi>c. 44.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What rootes are ill and good for the liuer. <hi>c. 45.
46.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What woodes are good or ill for this complexion. <hi>c. 47.
48.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What gummes are good or ill for this complexion. <hi>c. 49.
50.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Metridate, treacle, ſaffron in the time of peſtilence not
to be vſed of this complexion without direction in ſpeciall cauſe. <hi>c.
51.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The phlegmatick complexion why it is ſo called. <hi>c.
52.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Signes to know this complexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>c. 53.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>This complexion is apteſt to breed the infection. <hi>c.
54.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The diet for this complexion. <hi>c. 55.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What minerals and stones are ill for this complexion. <hi>c.
56. 57.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What hearbs, fruits, and other things are ill for this
com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion. <hi>c. 58.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Hearbes good to purge phleg. from the liuer and to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect
the qualities of phleg. in the liuer. <hi>c. 59.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Hearbes good for the breſt, heart and heart. <hi>c.
60.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Certaine things which this complexion may eat that others may
not. <hi>c. 61.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The manner how to purge this complexion whenſoeuer the
humour exceedeth. <hi>c. 62.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The meanes to purge the blood in this complexion. <hi>c.
63.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The water for this complexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to vſe as before in the
ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guine complexion. <hi>c. 64.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The perfume. <hi>c. 65.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The pome. <hi>c. 66.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The pilles. <hi>c. 67.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Reaſons wherefore the chole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick complexio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is not placed
next the ſanguine as diuers haue vſed. <hi>c. 68.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The aptnes of this complexion to draw it &amp; entertaine it.
<hi>c. 69.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Signes ſhewing this complexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>c. 70.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The diet for this complexion. <hi>c. 71.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>If the head or ſtomack be ouer hot abſtaine from things
in the <hi>c. 72. 73.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Directions how this complexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is to feede and from what to
abſtaine. <hi>c. 71.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What things this complexion is to forbeare is ſhewed.
<hi>c. <pb facs="tcp:10326:4"/> 74. 75.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What ſtones, what plantes, what fruites this complexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
may beſt vſe is ſhewed. <hi>c. 76, 77, 78.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The meanes to purge all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors in this complexion and
ſpecially choller. <hi>c. 79.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The meanes to purge the blood in this complexion. <hi>c.
80.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The water for this complexion. <hi>c. 81.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The perfume. <hi>c. 82.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A receipt for this complexion to take at any time in the time
of peſtilence. <hi>c. 83.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The pilles for this complexion in the time of peſtilence.
<hi>c. 84.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The pome for this complexion in the time of peſtilence.
<hi>c. 85.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What Melancholie is. <hi>c. 86.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The reaſon wherfore this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion is leaſt apt to take
this infection. <hi>c. 87.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Signes ſhewing this complexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>c. 88.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Things conuenient for this complexion. <hi>c. 89.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Things ill for this complexion. <hi>c. 90.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>VVhat things are to be vſed commonly, what not ſo
com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly. <hi>91, 92. 93.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Things good for the liuer and ſplene in this complexion.
<hi>c. 94, 95.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The purgation for all humors in this complexion and
ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially for exceſſe of melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholie. <hi>c. 96.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The receipt to clenſe the blood in this complexion. <hi>c.
97.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The water for this complexion to vſe in the time of
peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence vpon their clothes &amp; in their houſes. <hi>c.
98.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The bole for this complexion to vſe in the time of
peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence. <hi>c. 100.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The ſuffumigation. <hi>c. 99.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The pills. <hi>c. 101.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The pome. <hi>c. 102.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <div type="table_of_recipes">
               <head>General receipts in the time of peſtilence, by pome, pills,
&amp;c.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>The pomes. <hi>c. 104, 150.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The pills. <hi>c. 106.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The ponder and pills. <hi>c. 107. 108.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The perfume. <hi>c. 109, 110.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The water to ſprinkle and vſe as before. <hi>c.
111.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>A receipt to clenſe the blood, <hi>c. 112.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Signes ſhewing the heart or humours about the heart to be
infected with the peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence. <hi>c. 113, 114.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Meanes to know who is infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted. <hi>c. 115.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Meanes to know if any roomes be infected. <hi>c.
116.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:10326:5"/>Means to know which of the two that are
infected lying ſicke ſhall liue. <hi>c. 117.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Meanes to know who hath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſoare and whereabout. <hi>c.
118.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The order for thoſe which are ſhut vp beeing infected
or ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected. <hi>c. 119, 120, 121.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>No man can certenly ſet downe the cure for euery one
infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, neither cure the ſame, although it be not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmed at the heart,
the reaſon. <hi>c. 122.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:10326:5"/>
            <head>COMPLEXIONS Caſtle.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 1.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas the beginner, and preſeruer of all things, in his
word doth will vs to conſider his creatures, euen to the leaſt, Ecclus. 42.
v. 22. <hi>Oh how delecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble are all his workes, and to be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, euen
vnto the ſparks of fire:</hi> and <hi>to praiſe him without beeing
wearie,</hi> Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clus. chap. 43. v. 30. then how much more ought men daily with
chearefulnes, and diligence, conſider and regard the wonderfull order of
himſelfe, euen vnto the leaſt and baſeſt member, or part, which is of
more eſtimation, then a thouſand ſparkes of fire, and more to be wondred
at then any one element, becauſe it conſiſteth moſt wonderfully of all
the elements, and is that, for which they all, and all other things were made
and ordained. Then ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there is no earthly thing, that man ſhould more
regard and conſider then himſelfe, what meanes ſhould any man thinke to
be too much, to preſerue this rare and wonderfull order of man, in
conuenient, comely, and healthfull man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner? May not they be ſuſpected for
murtherers of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, which for idlenes, will not ſeeke, for ſparing
coſt, care not to ſeeke, which vpon malitious ſtomacke, and braſen
courage, contemne to ſeeke in time, the meanes the Lord hath left, to
preſerue and continue that wonderfull matter of man, in conuenient order?
Vnto theſe it happeneth moſt commonly, when extremitie of ſicknes hath
entred their ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, and ruine beginne to ruſh in, then none more
diligent, <pb n="2" facs="tcp:10326:6"/> none more liberall none more calme and tractable,
when all labour coſt, willingnes, and paines cannot preuaile. May not they be
ſuſpected of murther, who knowing a place in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with the peſtilence,
will preſume to enter, either by reaſon of intemperancie, not fearing, or
for gaine giue the aduenture? May not they likewiſe be ſuſpected of
murther, which knowing their houſes infected, not indeauour to vſe the
ordinarie meanes, either to ſhut it vp, and to flie from it, <hi>citò,
longè, tardè,</hi> or neceſſitie conſtraining to tarrie,
then, and there, to ſeeke the beſt meanes they may? May not they be
condemned for murtherers, which hauing plague ſoares, will preſſe into
companies to infect others, or wilfully pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute the ayre, or other meanes,
which others are daily to vſe, and liue by? The word of God commanded the
leper to haue his head bare, a couering for his lippes, his garments burnt, and
to crie, <hi>I am vncleane, I am vncleane,</hi> Leuit. 13.45. to the ende he
ſhould be knowne, and not infect the ayre with his breath: then how much more
ought they, to note themſelues by eſpeciall ſignes, and to keepe them
from in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting the ayre, hauing ſoares much more readie to infect then any
other diſeaſe. Furthermore, if man will not be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and conſider
this wonderfull order of his bodie, becauſe he knoweth that it muſt
periſh, he muſt know that he muſt neither appoint nor preuent the time:
beſide he muſt know that it is the cage of his ſoule, which muſt liue
for euer, &amp; therefore in honour of that beeing the image of God, keepe the
cage as cleane as he can, neither breake or diſſolue the ſame, leaſt
his ſoule, as an vntimely bird, flie vnto the hill. No bodie polluted with
groſſe humours, either with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, or defect of any humour, but it
is more apt to grieue the ſoule, defile the ſoule, and offend the creatour
of bodie and ſoule. Doth not exceſſe of choller cauſe men to rage? of
phlegme to be dull &amp; ſleepie? of melancholie to phren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie? and
ſubtiltie of blood to wantonneſſe? then perilous is the ſtate of the
bodie, whoſe ſpirits are poſſeſſed with the infection, a
propagation many times to deſpaire, and to forget all dutie, without Gods
eſpeciall grace. Is not he a ſimple man, which will entertaine a daily
aduerſarie to <pb n="3" facs="tcp:10326:6"/> dwell with him, which they doe, that admit
bad humours to haue domination in them, violating nature, or altering her, ſo
as ſhee is compelled to bring forth fruit like vnto her changed ſtate, that
it may be ſaid of ſome children in whom exceſſe of raging, dulnes,
craftines, wantonneſſe, dropſie, le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſie, phrenſie doe raigne:
while my parents ſlept, and were not watchfull to purge their natures, the
enemie, the malignant matter cauſed theſe tares of bad fruit to be ſowne
in me, which except grace doe gouerne, will exceede, ſo as there will be
little hope of any good fruit of me, becauſe my ſoyle is natural to bring
forth bad fruit, being thus cauſed by my parents: <hi>quod natura mihi dedit
aliernari neque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at,</hi> except Gods holy angel watch ouer me, and with the
blaſt or breath of the holy ſpirit winnow away my corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Now therfore
it behooueth parents to be no leſſe care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to purge and make cleane
their bodies from hurtfull hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, the cauſes of ill effects, then the
husbandman hath to purge and cleanſe his feede. If we haue a treſpaſſe,
or miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demeanour done in our goods or houſes, we ſeeke to amend it, but
if bad humours doe hazard our bodies, and aduenture our bodies to bring forth
bad fruit, or infruitles, before our time hazard death, we deferre the
ordinarie meanes, diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantaging nature, and art, her miniſter:
careleſſely cutting off the number of our daies, which God hath numbred in
his fore-knowledge, and by mediate meanes to be continued with our great care,
becauſe he firſt cared for vs, and daily continueth the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 2.</head>
               <p>THe law of nature calleth for a ſpeciall care and regard, to
preſerue euery member in order: for if ſhee be diſtempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the
leaſt, the principall members are diſquieted, and conſequently the whole
bodie: then what ſpeciall care ought man to haue in preſeruing the
naturall, vitall, and ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall members, the cauſe of increaſing, liuing,
moouing, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing, and beeing, not onely in office and dutie one for an
other, but all of them for man, and man for his maker. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are not onely
careleſſe to helpe nature in her order, but by exceſſe daily doe hurt
her in themſelues and others. God <pb facs="tcp:10326:7"/> hath giuen her to thee, for
thee, in thee, and with thee, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue his appointed time, and hath made
her a meanes to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine ſtrength, wiſdome, knowledge, learning,
delights, and pleaſures: all which doe lurke, if ſhee doe lower, all which
doe leaue to be, if ſhee be not to liue, beeing the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall life of man.
Iob. 34. v. 14. and in Levit. 17. v. 14. ſhee is called a <hi>ſpirit,</hi>
the next worthieſt vnto the ſoule in the ſeruice of God, thereupon it is
ſaid in the Pſalme, <hi>My ſoule doth magnifie the Lord, and my ſpirit
hath reioyced in God my Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our.</hi> This ſpirit which is the vapour of
blood, and becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth vitall, and animall, is the cage wherein the ſoule
moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth: the liuer, heart, and head, are the principall regions from whence
the ſpirit into all other members and parts doe paſſe, with the ſoules
power and effect, either good or bad, ſo that no member, neither the
ſpirit, not the ſoule can ſay to either, thou diddeſt this wickednes,
or goodneſſe without me, and therefore muſt receiue alike. Now then for
the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie of natures order pollute her not, diſtemper her not, but
indeauour to continue her, as God hath framed and ordained meanes for her.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 3.</head>
               <p>THe law of man requireth of thee to conſider, and inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to
preſerue thy body in conuenient order: for the ſtipend it alloweth for him,
that murdereth himſelfe, is baſe regarded, and vnreuerent vſage of the
corps, by markes vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their graues, in void and vild places, beſides the
loſſe of goods from wife &amp; children. Let men therefore take heede
leaſt by their negligence, wilfulnes, or couetuouſnes, they be not guiltie
thereof, before God and in their conſciences, and ſo be preuented of their
continuall ioy, for preuenting the Lords purpoſe heare a litle while, which
is to haue a man to liue the number of his daies in holines towards him, and in
dutifulnes to diſpatch, what God himſelfe, what king, countrie, and parents
plead for: which they cannot doe, that wilfully will take the meanes to
ſhorten their daies, or negligently omit the meanes, to hable them to recouer
to continue their daies. Thou art not only iniured, either by taking the
foreſaide meanes, or likewiſe omitting the meanes: but God, the parents,
king, and countrie may be <pb n="5" facs="tcp:10326:7"/> iniured, for great might be the
glory, which God might gayne by the reſt of thy daies, much might be the ioy
and comfort to thy parents, king, and countrie: therefore ſhorten not thy
daies wilfully, neither omit the meanes whereby there may be hope to redeeme
what wilfullie or negligently thou haſt hazarded to looſe of thy appoynted
time. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore, man is not onely charged with this watchfulnes, and care
ouer himſelfe, but he is charged with a care ouer o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, eſpecially ouer
ſuch as he hath charge: for if thou knoweſt the meanes to helpe to continue
the number of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>others daies, and be hable thereunto, thou muſt indeauour to
doe it, becauſe thou muſt doe, as thou would be done vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and alſo hope
of ſome of the fruites before named to come from that body: nay office, and
dutie, driueth euery one to helpe others, from ſicknes, ſoares, or dangers.
Art not thou which art a maſter or ſuperiour, bound to greeue for thy
ſeruant, and to releeue thy ſeruant or inferiour lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing, and yet
labouring about thy buſines? art not thou inferiour likewiſe bound to
greiue, and indeauour to releiue thy ſuperiour languiſhing, and yet
counſayling and caring for thee? Now therefore let ſuperiour, and inferiour
indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to continue the number of their daies, which to God (as I ſaid) is
certainly knowne, and to man vncertaine: yet men muſt certainely knowe, that
it is the ordinance of god, then not to be reſiſted, but in others, as well
as in our ſelues to be continued; by our beſt indeuours, becauſe we are
members one of another, and therefore ought ſenſiblie to feele ech others
greife and paſſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 4.</head>
               <p>THe ſoule crieth vnto thee to correct bad humours, and not
admit them to raigne: for when ſhe would be gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, mild, and patient, the
exceſſe of choller, conſtrayneth to rage and reuenge, when ſhe would
watch and pray, the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of phlegme, cauſeth ſleepines, and dulnes:
likewiſe the exceſſe of other humours, or the confounding of humours,
worketh effectes more vnkindly againſt the ſoule, for what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer is of
the fleſh, is oppugnant to the ſpirit, or ſoule, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till it hath
conuerted it, to bring forth together the fruits of <pb n="6" facs="tcp:10326:8"/> the
fleſh, which are badges not onely of an vnregenerate man, but of a
miſcreant, in ſoule and bodie. Seeing then the lawe of God, thy owne
ſoule, nature, the law of man, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, king, and country, commaund, and
call vnto thee to endeuour to preſerue thy bodie, by the almightie his meanes
left vnto the, and by his meanes to correct exceſſe of bad humours, and to
amend their confuſion, leaſt they here con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founding, ſoule, conſcience,
and vnderſtanding, god at thy firſt death confounde thy ſoule, and in the
laſt generall iudgement, thy confounded ſoule carry thy fleſh vnto the
place of confuſion. Therefore it is moſt neceſſarie for thee to know
thy complection, to know what humours abound in thee, or are deficient, or
whether they, or any of them be confounded or ſhuffled with nature, cauſing
alteration or confuſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 5.</head>
               <p>TO define the peſtilent feuer, is but to reiterate others
actions, neither much profitable to the vnlearned: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I purpoſe to
ſpend the time in that, which may tend vnto the good of the moſt, with the
leaſt ſuſpect of detracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or ambition. The peſtilent feuer is taken
not onely by infection in the ayre, infuſed by celeſtiall orbes, and from
putrified places, in and vpon the earth: but alſo by bad hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours about the
heart and ill affected ſpirits in the heart, whoſe aptitude doth entertaine
the ſaid infection, yet not alike in all, for all then ſhould die alike:
but according to the complection, it is taken ſooner or ſlower, in greater
quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie or leſſe, and according to the virulent qualitie, or quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
in the ayre, taken ſooner or ſlower, and according to the ſubiect
ſooner or ſlower deſtroying: as in the humours a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the heart, and the
ſpirits in the heart, in the one ſlow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, in the other ſooner, becauſe
the vitall and animall are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed more ſpeedily: thereupon it commeth
when any are thus wiſe affected, they are exceeding hot, they rage, they
cannot ſtand, and die quickly, or ſuddenly, in the other, ſoores often
times doe ſaue, becauſe nature doth purge hir ſelfe, by the emunctory
places. But if they doe not breake forth, the virulent matter returning to the
places about the <pb n="7" facs="tcp:10326:8"/> heart, there doth remaine, and kindleth
exceeding beat, whereby the heart &amp; ſpirits therein contained are
inflamed, and all naturall humiditie thereby conſumed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 6.</head>
               <p>THe qualities vnnaturally working in the ayre from the
celeſtiall orbes, and maſſie globe, are ouer much hotnes and moyſtnes,
actiuely working in the ayre, and all three in the humours and ſpirits of
man: the ſooner, by the aptitude of complection and ſeaſon, or the time
of the yeare, altering the qualities naturall, both in complection and ayre, in
ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſooner, in winter ſlower, in the one, becauſe there is
ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halation, of putrified vapours, and heate exceeding, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing it to be
more virulent: in the other, becauſe of the <hi>anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periſtaſin</hi> of
the could qualitie in the ayre, which doth alter the hotnes infuſed from
aboue, and diuert or turne back the hot putrified qualitie lower into the
earth, where the cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the earth doth alter it, and the drynes retayne
it.</p>
               <p>The ſubſtance or matter putrifying in the humours or
ſpirits of man, is ayre impure: thicker then ayre naturall, by reaſon of
moiſture, yet not ſo thicke as water or myſts; by reaſon of heat:
hotter then ayre naturall, yet not ſo drie by reaſon of exceſſe of
moiſture.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 7.</head>
               <p>THe reaſon wherefore it doth putrifie in the humours or
ſpirits of man, is the exceſſe of heat or moiſture, putrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the
aire, conueied thither: the one inflaming, the other cauſe of continuing or
retaining, by reaſon of the denſitie or thicknes. Secondly, aptnes in the
ſubiects to entertaine the fame. And thirdly large paſſages to conuey the
ſame to the ſubiects, and in all, a diſparance from the ſubſtance and
qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities of the ayre, and of the naturall humours and ſpirits in man.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 8.</head>
               <p>IF the ſubſtance of the ayre be infected, then not onely
men, but birds, beaſts, hearbs, and plants will die.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 9.</head>
               <p>IF the aire be infected in qualitie, then men, and birdes may
die by it, more or leſſe, ſooner or ſlower, according <pb facs="tcp:10326:9"/> to
the quantitie of the virulent matter receiued, &amp; according to the quantitie
of virulent and putrified matter in the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, and according to the aptnes
in the ſubiects, either by large paſſages letting it in, and beeing
within, inhabilitie of contrarie qualities to expell the ſame.</p>
               <p>If putrefaction be in the qualite of the ayre, that it is ouer
hotte and groſſe, or more hot then groſſe, as commonly it is, then it
is good for the cholericke and ſanguine, to dwell in low roomes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 10.</head>
               <p>THeſe are ſignes, ſhewing the ayre to be infected in
qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie the next yeare following: in autumne before, there will be
flaſhings of fyre, and many meteors of vnequall ſhapes, in the ſpring
following could and little rayne, in the ſpring and ſommer, the wind moſt
South-ward, great heate in the day, and the night very cold.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 11.</head>
               <p>THeſe are the ſignes ſhewing the ayre to be infected in
ſubſtance and qualitie, the effect continuing ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer and winter, and the
next ſpring following: the reaſon is, if the ayre, the winter before, had
beene infected only in qualitie, then the contrarie would haue corrected it,
which to iudgement whas as hable, as in other winters. Secondly, paſſions
ſenſible felt and ſeene, in bodies, in the hearbs, in the ayre, and from
the earth, like as was the yeare or ſpring before. Thirdly, the euent in
places more generall, where no meanes came, but the ayre to infect.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 12.</head>
               <p>IF the putrefaction proceedeth moſt of the earth or
vpper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt partes of the earth, as from ſtinking channells, ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
lakes, priuyes, or other polluted places, as dunghills, vncleane kept houſes,
and ſuch like, then there will be felt many ſudden great ſtinches, and
vnſauerie ſmells, ſuch as cannot be diſtinguiſhed, or diſcerned,
what it is, or whereof it commeth, becauſe it is confounded, beeing made of
di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers ſtinches: in that yeare there wil be many frogges, toades, venemous
wormes, fleas, and flyes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:10326:9"/>
               <head>CHAP. 13.</head>
               <p>IF the putrefaction proceedeth from within the earth, then
venemous beaſts and wormes will be ſeene more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly aboue the earth,
and will breede vpon the earth, and many of them will die.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 14.</head>
               <p>THe putrefaction or virulent matter of infection now, is from
celeſtiall orbes principally, alſo from corrupt pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, partly from
corrupt humours in man, begotten by the two former, and ill order in feeding
and ſleeping, in idlenes and late walking abroad, and ſitting vp.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 15.</head>
               <p>THe infection taken at the noſtrills is more daungerous then
otherwiſe, becauſe there are two organes or paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that lead to the
heart, from thence more, then from the mouth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 16.</head>
               <p>THe putrified aire cannot paſſe ſo ſpeedily to mans
heart, as to diuers other creatures by the inſtrument of ſmel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, which
is couered with a pellicle or filme, which is to be lifted vp before he can
ſmell by the ayre or fume: and that pellicle is groſſer in man then in
other creatures: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore requireth the hotter or ſtronger fume to
mooue it. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, the inſtrument of ſmelling is placed deeper in the
head, then in any other creatures. Thirdly, the inſtrument of ſmelling is
nigh the braine in man, which with the moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture doth hinder the naturall
complexion of the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſmelling, which is hot and drie,
attractiue or draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vnto it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 17.</head>
               <p>IF the putrefaction in the ayre be more hot then moiſt, then
it is more apt to deſtroy, and to be taken by the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrills: firſt,
becauſe the heat is ſubtile, and paſſeth vp ſpeedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the
pellicle, and mooueth with the fume or moiſture. Secondly, for that the heat
doth reſiſt the coldnes and moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture of the braine, the which are
hinderers of ſmelling.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 18.</head>
               <p>The complexion apteſt to be infected, is the ſanguine, 
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:10326:10"/> firſt, becauſe the qualities in that complexion are
like vnto the qualities in the ayre, hot and moiſt, and therefore doth
entertaine the ayre the apter. Secondly, becauſe theſe two qualities in
this complexion maketh it more conuertible, like the ayre, which will ſooner
be made hotter or moiſter then any of the other elements. Thirdly, becauſe
in this complexion, the paſſages leading to the humours about the heart,
and to the vitall ſpirits in the heart, are more large and ſpatious then in
any other. The reaſon is, for that blood na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall is not without his
vapours, which cauſe motion, and where moſt motion of blood is, there is
cauſe of extention, and the ſame is in this complexion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 19.</head>
               <p>The apteſt time for this complexion to entertaine the
vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rulent matter into the humours, is in the former ſpring eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially: for
then blood increaſeth, and paſſeth vp and downe, beeing not thoroughly
refined, and made the readier by his motion and impuritie to receiue it.</p>
               <p>The apteſt time for this complexion to entertaine the
vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rulent matter into the ſpirits vitall is ſommer, by reaſon that the
blood beeing made hot, and the ſpirits likewiſe hot, and ayre continually
heating.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 20.</head>
               <p>This complexion may take the infection, although not at the
noſtrills or mouth, yet it may take it at the emuncto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie places, and at the
pores in the skin in other places, which are more large and readier to be
opened, then in the other complexions.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 21.</head>
               <p>The ſignes ſhewing this complexion. Viſage, white and
ruddie, moſt redde in the cheekes, eyes orderly placed, yet ſomewhat large
ofttimes, vaines blew and full, pulſe full and great, vrine plentie, redde
and ofttimes groſſe, ſeege, and ſweat exceeding, digeſtion perfect,
apt to bleeding and ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, willing to mooue, yet abſtaining from
motion, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of heate and ſweating, ſubiect to dreame of bloodie
things, and amorous toyes, affable, affectionate, yet to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooued, well
ſpoken, chaungeable in opinion, apt to haue <pb n="11" facs="tcp:10326:10"/> the yellow
iaundes, heat vnder the lites, at the heart, and raines, ſtitch in the right
ſide, ſubiect to the chollicke, and then the hands and face will be full of
ſrecks in many a one, of meane ſtature and comely for the moſt part, a
louer of muſicke and wines, effeminate, beard large and comely, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfull
in himſelfe, a louer of companie and conuertible with them, merrie for the
moſt part, haire of colour red or yellowiſh, ſubiect to the feuer called
Synocham. This com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion hauing taken the infection in the humors about the
heart, in the emunctorie places, or at the pores in the skin, beeing come vnto
the blood, may beſt of any complexion haue a vaine opened.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 22.</head>
               <p>IF this complection or any other, haue the blood infected, the
vaines will be blackiſh, and not ſo full, as before in health, for that the
good blood flyeth inward to the ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from the infection, and there
remaineth ſubiect to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection by little and little, as it goeth outward, or
as the other runneth inward, the liuer will be worſe in this complection, and
conſequently digeſtion imperfect, the body hot all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, more then in
other complections, becauſe blood infec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted hath larger paſſage, then in
other complections. For aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as good blood is not without good vapour, and
both of them, cauſe of vitall ſpirit, and that cauſe of the animall
ſpirits, by which two man liueth, and mooueth, and is made more hable to
reſiſt the virulent matter of peſtilence: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it behooueth euery
complection to clenſe his blood, &amp; purge it from humours hurtfull vnto
it, which theſe receipts following by Gods helpe will performe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 23.</head>
               <p>TAke of caſſia new extracted one ounce, of hony halfe an
ounce, of ſugar two drammes, infuſe theſe ſeuen or eight howers, in
fowre ounces of borrage water, and ſower oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of violet or endiue water:
if you can, get a fingerfull of liuerwoort, and firſt bruiſe it a little,
then infuſe it with the caſſia, it will be very proper, (eſpecially if
it be in ſommer) then ſtrayne all together, and drinke of it euery morning
faſting, three howers before meate, the quantitie of two or 
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:10326:11"/> three ounces, vntill you feele your blood reaſonable
cooled, and the ſtomack not impayred.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 24.</head>
               <p>IF this complection doth learne or perceiue, that choller
raigneth in the blood, then let them take the quantitie of Caſſia, hony,
and ſugar before mentioned, and of Rhubarbe three dra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes, of the ſweete
ruſh called ſquinant, one dra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me, pound them all groſſ, then infuſe
them ſeauen or eight howers in ſeauen ounces of water of endiue, or
cichorie, or for want of theſe, in the decoction <hi>florum &amp;
fructum,</hi> to the which put of ſyrupe of roſes laxatiue, and of
ſyrrupe of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olets of either halfe an ounce: take it two mornings or three
together, warme it a little before you take it, &amp; take it ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what
colder then blood-warme.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 25.</head>
               <p>IF this complexion doth ſpie, that phlegme be mixt with the
blood, then let him take of Turbith, or Agaricke, two drammes, ginger two
ſcruples, and pound them groſſ, or ſlice them thin, and infuſe it
with halfe an ounce of Caſſia and an ounce of hony if it be in winter: at
other times take as much caſſia as hony, and infuſe all together in eight
or nine ounces of ſweete wine, or Oximell, that is, one part vineger, twyſe
ſo much hony, foure times ſo much water boyled vntill the third part be
waſted, and cleane skimmed: take this two mornings faſting.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 26.</head>
               <p>IF melancholie raygne take of caſſia and hony one ounce,
&amp; of polypody one dramme, a ſcruple and a halfe of gin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, cut the
polypody and ginger very thin, and infuſe them altogether, in ſix or
ſeauen ounces of fumitory water eight howers: then ſtrayne them and drinke
it warme faſting two mornings together: when you take any of theſe you
muſt ſit a quarter of an hower, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> walke as long, then lie vpon your
right ſide, then vpon your left as long, that done, then ſit vp tight halfe
an hower, after that walke and ſit at your pleaſure in your chamber.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 27.</head>
               <p>Hauing cleanſed your blood, and auoided the bad hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, 
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:10326:11"/> which moſt annoy you, (which is meete to be done, in
euery one once a yeare, in many twiſe, in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer and latter ſpring,
(and in ſome oftener) then will your blood and ſpirits be leſſe capable
of the infection, and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hable to expell it, hauing taken it, and ſo
much the leſſe capable and hable, by how much you ſhallbe carefull to
vſe theſe receiptes following, beſt fitting for your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 28.</head>
               <p>FIrſt a receipt very proper to be taken, not onely, as a
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſatiue euery morning faſting, but for your reſolution to knowe,
whether you be infected, for then you will vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite or at leaſt be very full,
and deſirous to vomite, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the contrarietie of the qualities in
theſe ſubſtances, &amp; the virulent heate in your owne ſubſtance.
Send vnto the Apothecaries billes made as followeth: <hi>R. Santalorum omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,
Boliarmenei ana ſcr.</hi> 2. <hi>aq. roſar. dr.</hi> 2. <hi>aq. violarum
dr.</hi> 3. <hi>vini albi. dr.</hi> 5. infuſe theſe in the waters and the
wine 7. or 8. houres, then ſtraine them through a very courſe ſtrainer,
and drinke it faſting, or before ſupper an houre and halfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 29.</head>
               <p>A Pome very comfortable, and neceſſarie for this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion
to vſe at all times, and eſpecially in the time of peſtilence. <hi>R.
Santalorum omnium dr. 2. florum Boraginis, Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larum, Roſarum rub. ana dr. 1.
ſ. rad. Cichorij dr. 1. Macis dr. 2. Cort. mali citri dr. 1. ſ. Camphurae
dr. 2. Ladan. d 1. Papaneris albi ſcr. 1. Ambrae gra. 2. Cinamomi d. 5.
cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Teribenthina in
aq<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſarum Lot. in qua fiat dr. 1. ſtoracis infuſio hor. 7.</hi> Smell
vnto this at any time, but cheifely faſting, and when meate is
digeſted.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 30.</head>
               <p>A Water to ſprinckle vpon cloathes, and in the houſe, meete
for this complexion at all times, and in the time of peſtilence moſt
neceſſarie. <hi>R. olei violarum, Nenupharij ana d.</hi> 2. <hi>olei
roſarum vn. s. Camphurae vn.</hi> 5. <hi>omnium Santalorum vn.</hi> 3.
<hi>Thuris dr.</hi> 2. <hi>Myrrhae vn. s. Cort. Limonum citrinorum &amp;
granatum ana dr.</hi> 1. <hi>Tamariſe, Ribes. Coriand. ana vn. s.</hi> When
you haue gotten theſe, or ſo many as you can of them, then 
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:10326:12"/> cut them or pound them groſſe, and boile them in two
quarts of vineger, or one quart of vineger, and the other of water, vntill a
pint be conſumed, then put in your oyles and gummes, and ſtoppe the
veſſell very cloſe, and let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> boile halfe a quarter of an houre.
Straine it before it be colde through a coarſe ſtrainer very hard, then put
to it of roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water vn. 2. and mixe it well with it then put it into a
glaſſe ſtopped cloſe, and ſet it out of the ſunne: when you would
vſe it, ſtirre it well together before you put in the bruſh or ſponge,
becauſe of the oyles which will flote and be vpper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt. This may ſerue
any complexion, the better for the chollericke, if you doe adde more of the
cold and moyſt things, as of the oyle of lillies, violets, of the lemmons,
orin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and pomegranates, and ſuch like, which the Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries may doe,
if you informe them of your complexion: the better for the phlegmatike, if he
diminiſh of the cold and moiſt things, the quantitie following, and adde of
theſe things; <hi>origani p j. Thuris ar.</hi> 2. <hi>cipreſſiar.</hi> 2.
<hi>Iuniperi dr.</hi> 3. the better for the melancholie, if you adde of oyle of
ſweete al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds, and oyle of nutmegges, dr. 3. of muske gr. 4. <hi>coſti
dulc. gr.</hi> 2.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 31.</head>
               <p>A Perfume proper for this complexion, and good for all, to alter
the virulent qualitie in the aire about thee. <hi>R. nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis moſchat, caphur,
nardi, garyopillorum, ana dr. s. ladani, cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, ana dr.</hi> 1.
<hi>ſtiracis dr. s. ſantali albi odoriferi, benionini ana dr.</hi> 3.
<hi>ciperi dr.</hi> 1 <hi>s. fol. roſarum rub. dr.</hi> 2. <hi>matorani, fol
lauria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na dr. s ligni aloes dr. s. omnia in puluerem redact. commixta<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>
cum aqua roſarum, in qua tragagant. gummi arabicum, ſiue ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phura
maduerint, formenter paſtilli, ſiue orbiculi pro ſuffimento.</hi> Then
may you at pleaſure take ſome of it and perfume with it, as with other
perſumes. Vſe the perfume in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone, then the water in the
afternoone: let all the houſhold be preſent to take the perfume,
eſpecially thoſe of this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion. This will laſt or continue three
daies in your roomes, or in your apparell, the longer if you vſe the water
preſently after the perfume, for the oyles, and the apparell will retaine it
a long time, which others that come nigh you, <pb n="15" facs="tcp:10326:12"/> or talke
with you will diſcouer, eſpecially if the water pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed for the
plegmatike be vſed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 32.</head>
               <p>Theſe pills are good for this complexion, but beſt to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
winter, or in winter: for the often vſing in ſommer may procure a feuer.
<hi>R. Aloes dr.</hi> 2. <hi>lot. in vino alb. &amp; aqua violarum ſiue
Endiuie, ſucci acaciae. dr. s. myrrhe, cinamoni ana dr.</hi> 1. <hi>fiat
maſſa pillularum cum vino &amp; aqua boraginis, ſine ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chorij.</hi> If
you haue the hemorehoids, or if women haue their ſicknes, then tell the
Apothecaries, and will him to adde to the former, <hi>bdellij ſubalbidi. dr.
s.</hi> and thereby you ſhall be ſure of no harme to the intralls: adde
this <hi>Dragaganthi dr. s.</hi> take the waight of halfe a dramme in pills,
before you goe forth, or before ſupper, but drinke preſently after a little
draught either of ale or white wine. Whoſoeuer doe vſe theſe pills, they
ſhall finde for their complexion a great be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit to the head and
ſpirits.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 33.</head>
               <p>IT is very good for this complection in ſommer to vſe this,
<hi>R. Tamarirind. dact. vn. 2. fiat infuſio ſiue decoctio in ſero lactis
lib. 1. s.</hi> and drinke of it two mornings, you may take this, when you
will, ſo that it be not preſently after ſupper or dinner before
digeſtion be made: if you will haue it taſt ſharpe, put into it the more
of the Tamarindes. I would wiſh euery complection in the time of peſtilence
in ſommer to vſe this, but mooue not violently preſently after you haue
taken it: this will procure appetite and coldnes, and kindlie purgeth
choller.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 34.</head>
               <p>IF this complection ſuſpect, that they haue taken the
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, then let them put their legges in warme water, &amp; be let blood
in the vaines, which lead from the heart and head.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 35.</head>
               <p>IT is very good in the time of peſtilence for this
complexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to vſe frication in the morning, eſpecially of their thighes
and legges.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="chapter">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:10326:13"/>
               <head>CHAP. 36.</head>
               <p>IT is good for this complection to drinke in the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone of
a ptiſme made of barly, adding to it a little vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, to euery pynt halfe a
ſpoonefull.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 37.</head>
               <p>IT it good for this complection, to vſe vineger in their
meates, and to wet their chamber flores with vineger,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 38.</head>
               <p>THeſe things are at no time conuenient for this complexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to
vſe, but worſt in the time of peſtilence, for their exceeding heat,
beeing hot in the fourth degree: garlicke, leekes, garding creſſes,
pepperwort, onyons, radiſh roots, neither are theſe conuenient eſpecially
in the time of peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, becauſe they properly heate the liuer, and
inflame the blood, wormewood, egrimonie, fennell, hyſſope, ſpike,
margerom, folefoote, time, harts tounge, all hearbes, which are hot in the
third degree, as rhue, ſauine, cloues, mynt, penyriall, veruin, ſmalledge,
perſlie, centorie, laurell, three-leaued graſſe, ſaffron, ſpourge,
the flowers of eldern are ill for the liuer, becauſe they heat it, the
flowers of betonie, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>momill, centorie, the flowers of Squinant called the
ſweete ruſh.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 39.</head>
               <p>Theſe hearbs are good for this complexion eſpecially in the
time of peſtilence, beeing colde in the ſecond degree; Lettice, cichorie,
ſorrell, beetes, Endiue, liuerwoort, crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toes, fleewoort, plantin,
knotgraſſe: and theſe likewiſe are good becauſe they properly coole
the liuer: fumitorie, wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terlillies, purſlayne: but moſt properly theſe
coole the liuer beeing eaten: cichorie, lettice, enduie, liuerwoort, the
flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of cichorie, water lillies, and red roſes are likewiſe good to
coole the liuer.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 40.</head>
               <p>THeſe are not conuenient for this complexion: fleſh of old
beaſtes, vdders, braynes, fat (eſpecially of fleſh) hot bread, much
ſleep, bloodinges, or intralles of beaſtes, mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, rawe hearbes, (except
borage cichorie, or lettice) nue ale, hard cheeſe, Fenniſh flowers are
ill.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="chapter">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:10326:13"/>
               <head>CHAP. 41.</head>
               <p>THeſe are good for this complexion, bread of wheate ſomwhat
leauened, well baked, not ouer ould: wines well fined, and of meates, thoſe
which are of good digeſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, not ouer ſweete, nor ouer eaſely to be
digeſted.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 42.</head>
               <p>OF fruites ſealdome vſe theſe: Iuniper buries, cloues, for
they are hot in the third degree, but leſſe ſeldome theſe, long pepper,
white pepper, blacke pepper, for they are hot in the fourth degree.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 43.</head>
               <p>EAte ſeldome figges, capers, dry meats, for theſe are hot in
the ſecond degree, and ſo are nutmegges, which heate the heart very much in
this complexion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 44.</head>
               <p>OF fruites theſe are good for the liuer: barberries, guords,
cucumbers, for they properlie coole the liuer, ſo are limonds, millions,
prunes, peaches pomegarnets, oringes ſomewhat tart, theſe are cold in the
ſecond degree.</p>
               <p>Of ſeedes theſe are ill for this complexion, for they heate
the liuer: aniſe ſeede, perſely ſeede, cummin ſeede, fennell ſeede,
wild ſmalledge ſeede, caraway ſeede, garding pepper ſeede, perſnipp
ſeede. Theſe ſeedes coole the liuer: guord, cucumers, endiue, lettice,
milion, purſlanie, citron ſeedes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="45" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 45.</head>
               <p>OF rootes theſe are ill for this complxion, for they heate the
liuer: ſmaledge, fennell, perſely, ſparage, rhue, butcher broome.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="46" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 46.</head>
               <p>SIchorie rootes and ſuch like before mentioned, are good to
coole the liuer.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="47" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 47.</head>
               <p>THe vſe of theſe wooddes are good for this complexion:
<hi>cypreſſe, the tamariske, ſantalum rub. alb. citrinum.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="48" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 48.</head>
               <p>THeſe not ſo good: the iuniper, guiacum, the wood alo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es,
the hebene tree, box tree, red ſtyrax, milleldine, the cedar tree.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="49" type="chapter">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:10326:14"/>
               <head>CHAP. 49.</head>
               <p>Theſe gummes for this complexion are good: the Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bicke and
Camphure.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="50" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 50.</head>
               <p>Theſe ill: the gumme of the Cedar, and the gumme
<hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniacum,</hi> beeing hot in the third degree; but theſe worſt of
all, <hi>Euphorbium,</hi> and the gumme <hi>Belzoin,</hi> for they are hot in
the fourth degree.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="51" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 51.</head>
               <p>Let this complexion take heede in taking Methridate, treacle,
ſaffron, and ſuch like, which oft times are meanes to inflame, and procure
ſores whereas there would be none, and the malignant matter, by leſſe
dangerous meanes, or by natures habilitie might be preuented.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="52" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 52.</head>
               <p>The phlegmatike complexion is ſo called, by the two qualities
in the water, cold and moiſtnes, combined and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dominant in a bodie;
conſiſting likewiſe of the other three elements, yet principally
participating of this, and thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hath the denomination phlegmaticke,
<hi>videl.</hi> cold &amp; moiſt for the moſt part.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="53" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 53.</hi> Signes to know this complexion.</head>
               <p>The ſubſtance ſoft, foggie, quauing: the colour of the
ſubſtance whitiſh, the proportion large, for the moſt part, or els
exceeding groſſe: veines hardly ſeene, blood wateriſh, pulſe ſlowe,
the bodie ſlowe in motion, ſleepie, dull, haire plaine, ſieldome bald,
not apt to learne, cowardiſh, ſpittle white, and after motion very frothie:
vrine groſſe &amp; white, eſpecially after great labour; ſubiect to
dreame of waterie things, as of fiſh and ponds: much ſuperfluitie or
excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments by ſpitting and ſweating: the feete ſtinking, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
after motion: the bodie ſubiect to his naturall infirmitie in Februarie
betweene the tenth day and the twentieth: this complexion is ſubiect to paine
in the head, loynes, knees, priuities, armes, and feete, by phlegmatike humours
taking cold: fearefull, timorous, the breaſt commonly without haire,
ſieldome angrie, not retaining anger, ſoone cold, the <pb n="19" facs="tcp:10326:14"/>
breaſt commonly narrow, and theſe are ſubiect to the ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the
heart, and much ſubiect to a quotidian feuer.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="54" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 54.</head>
               <p>This complexion is apteſt to breede the infection, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
moiſture doth cauſe putrefaction, eſpecially in the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſpring, and
winter: becauſe then phlegme raigneth, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing groſſe humours, that is
to ſay, making blood thicke, phlegme thicke, and choller groſſe,
retaining heat vnnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, which by heate in ſommer is made more hot and
viru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent expelling putrefaction. You muſt vnderſtand, that I write vpon
the phlegmatike bodie, as he is ſaid ſo to be na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally of phlegme, which
is cold and moiſt, ſweete, &amp; white, without diſtinction in taſt,
for that taſteth all other things: the ſubſtance, the forme, the
paſſions, the accidents of the phlegmaticke, which hath phlegme vnnaturall,
are diuers: for ſome is ſlimie, ſome ſalt, ſome viſcous, ſome
ſower, pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie, ſtipticke, thicke, groſſe, ſome thin: before all
or any of the which phlegme naturall was, and by diſtemperature, it becommeth
as before, which for the moſt part, is by exceſſe of phlegme naturall,
and by accidents comming to it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="55" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 55.</hi> The diet for the phlegmaticke.</head>
               <p>Hot things moderately vſed are good for this complex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion, for
they doe attenuate and digeſt phlegme. Eate of one meate at a meale, if not,
then eate the fineſt firſt, els the groſſe meates ſuffocate, and the
fineſt lie vndigeſted, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the coldnes in the ſtomacke, which
cannot digeſt the groſſe meates ſo ſpeedily as other complexions.
They muſt abſtaine from ſuch meates as ingender phlegme ouermuch, and are
cold and ſlimie, clammie or clung: new cheefe ill, all fiſh for the moſt
part, the beſt are ſmall fiſhes fried: the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards of beaſts ill,
repletion or feeding to the full ill, for concoction in the phlegmaticke is
ſlower then others, and therefore they ought of all others to ſatisfie
nature, not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite. Idlenes is ill, for agitation procureth heate and
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction, although it may be alledged that the ſtomacke is neuer idle, nor
out of motion in any complexion, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not onely the ſtomacke, but
all the bodie deſireth not <pb n="20" facs="tcp:10326:15"/> to mooue, but to be quiet and
ſtill: euen as the water which mooueth not, except the winde mooue it, or the
ſtraightens or highnes of the place force it to mooue.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="56" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 56.</head>
               <p>Theſe mineralls are ill for this complexion to vſe, in
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of their coldnes: quickſiluer, lead, white lead, burnt lead, ſpume
of ſiluer, or the dragges of lead.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="57" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 57.</head>
               <p>Theſe ſtones are likewiſe ill for their coldnes: the
car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buncle called a corneol, the ſaphyre ſtone, the chriſtall, the granat
ſtone, and this worſt, the diamant, for it is cold in the fourth degree,
likewiſe corall pearle is ill.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="58" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 58.</head>
               <p>Things cold in the firſt or ſecond degree, or moiſt in the
firſt or ſecond degree, are not vtterly to be forbidden to this complexion;
becauſe they worke not extremely, but may properly be corrected, by things
hot and drie in the ſecond degree, and ſo made temperate. But things
moiſt, or cold in the third or fourth degree, are ſieldome or neuer to be
vſed: for their correctiues muſt be equipollent, and then very of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten there
happeneth to the qualities of the other humours, no little diſtemperature.
Vſe this ſieldome, Mandrags, houſeleeke, henbane; theſe neuer,
humblocke, poppie, gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den-hearb (otherwiſe called orch:) forbeare ſorrell,
lettice, purſlaine, violets, waterlillies, endiue, cichorie, fumitorie,
plantin, borage, nightſhade, white roſes and redde. Eate ſiel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of
ſharpe oringes, peares, prunes: more ſieldome of gourds, cucumers, of
apples ſharpe and moiſt, pomegra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets, lemmons, millions, peaches, grapes.
Vſe theſe ſieldom, barly, millet (otherwiſe called Turkiſh wheat)
mallowſeed, rapeſeede. Refraine from cypreſſe wood, the Tamariske tree,
<hi>lignum trium ſantalorum,</hi> veriuice, vineger, and the iuice of
<hi>opium,</hi> the iuice of an Indian tree called <hi>ſanguinem
draco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uis,</hi> campher. Thoſe things which are cold and drie in the firſt
or ſecond degree, or cold in the firſt and ſecond degree and drie in the
third, may beſt be tolerated to be vſed in the time of peſtilence of this
complexion, then at other times.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="59" type="chapter">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:10326:15"/>
               <head>CHAP. 59.</head>
               <p>Theſe are conuenient for this complexion, becauſe they
aboliſh phlegme from the liuer and blood; wormewood, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimonie, fennell,
hyſſope, ſpicke, margerom. Theſe are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient, becauſe they doe
correct the colde qualitie of phlegme at the heart: balme, mynt, ſage,
borrage, bugloſſe, baſell.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="60" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 60.</head>
               <p>Theſe likewiſe are conuenient for the breaſt; horehound,
betonie, mayden haire, the nettle, dragon woort, and of theſe many are
conuenient for the head and other places. It is good for this complexion to
vſe Cinamon, Frankincenſe, hoppes, calamynt, and ſometime Rhue, and mace
is good, (although it be hot in the third degree) becauſe it is aroma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall
and cordiall, water-germander, colewoort, penyriall, perſly, the rootes of
penyriall, carriot rootes, galinga, fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell, rapes, zedoarie, perſly, the
ſea onyon, coriander ſeede, dill ſeede, aniſe ſeede, ſmalledge,
tocket, perſly ſeede, ſweete Almonds, Iuiubs, cypreſſe nuts, figges,
capers, nutmegges, cloues now and then, flowers of roſemarie, and lauender,
ſaffron, but not often in the time of infection, melilot, ſlae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chados,
bugloſſe, cammomill, the flowers of the ſweet ruſh, the flower of our
ladies roſe, garding pepper, Iamine, ſweete amber, and ſperma caeti, (or
parma caeti) the drie skumme or froth of the ſea; it is good to vſe the
ſtone that glaſiers cut their glaſſe with, called an emrod, the
Ancarcaſite or fire ſtone, the blood ſtone.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="61" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 61.</head>
               <p>THis complexion may eate onyons, and garlicke orderlie, ſo as
there is no diſtemperance, in the naturall humors by choller. Much vſe of
ſalt, groſſe pepper with meates are conuenient: greeneginger, and
myrabolans condite, very conuenient: keepe the head and feete warme: dwell in
high, and dry places: moderate ſweating is good.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="62" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 62.</head>
               <p>IT is very meete for this complexion, to purge once a yeare at
the leaſt, in the firſt ſpring when it is well entered, with this receipt
following, finding no ſpeciall cauſe to the <pb n="22" facs="tcp:10326:16"/>
contrarie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>R. Turpeti dr. 5. fol. ſen. dr. 10. polypodiidr. 2.
Hermodact dr. 2. s. Rhabarb dr. 2. Zuigib dr. 1. cinamomi aniſi ana ſcr.
5.</hi> when you haue all theſe, ſlyce them, and pound the aniſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeede
groſſe, then ſeeth them in a pynt and halfe of water, vntill the third
part be conſumed, then take of it faſting three ounces, and put to it an
ounce of ſyrupe of roſes laxatiue: take this three mornings together if you
ſee that your body be not ſufficiently purged in two mornings: which the
ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crementes, and your drynes or ſleepines will ſhewe: if that ſlyme, or
water come not, or ſlime ſomwhat yellowiſh com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and no wateriſh, or
white ſlime matter, then purge no more. So ſoone as you haue done purging
take this, <hi>R. Iu lap yiolat vn. 5. aq cinamomi aq. borag. ſiue endiuiae
vn. 5.</hi> this will qualifie the diſtemperature made by the purge, and will
comfort properly.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="63" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 63.</head>
               <p>VVIthin a fortnight after, to clenſe the blood, take this
receipt: <hi>R. Caſſiae nouiter extractae, mellis ana. vn. 5.</hi> infuſe
it in halfe a pint of ſweete wine, in <hi>vn. 2.</hi> of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage water,
drinke this two mornings faſting.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="64" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 64.</head>
               <p>THe water, proper to this complexion for vſe in the time of
peſtilence, or at other times, make it as it is for the ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guine
complexion adding vnto it, of oyle of ſweete al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mondes vn. 1. of
frankenſcence dr. 3. iuniper, vn. s. of ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pres vn. 1. of cloues vn. s. of
oyle of dill vn. 1. ſweete amber dr. 2. let there be a pint of vineger, and a
pynt and a halfe of coſe water put vnto it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="65" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 65.</head>
               <p>The perfume for this complexion, is to be made, and vſed as
for the ſanguin, ſauing, in ſtead of gum arabicke, vſe the gum myrrhe,
and ſtorax, or in ſtead of them <hi>gummi am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniacum,</hi> as much as is
conuenient for the making of the maſſe ſomewhat liquid.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="66" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 66.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Pome for this complexion:</hi> R. Santalornus odoriferum
d. s. fol. roſarum damaſc. d. 2. Ambr. odor. gr. 3. calamynt. dr. 2. 
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:10326:16"/> gummi Thuris dr. 2. macis d. <hi>1.</hi> ſ. Anethi dr.
1. nucis moſchat. d. 2. gariophillorum dr. 1. galing. d. 1. ſ. florum
Chammomil. d. ſ. ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rac. d. ſ. cinamom d. 2. moſc. gr. 2. ladani d. 1.
cum Terebint. in aq. roſarum &amp; miliſſa lot. vel potius in liq.
ſtiracis, fiat pom.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="67" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 67.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>The pylls for this complexion:</hi> R. Aloes lot. in vino
odorife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro, &amp; in aqua Chammomelini, ſiue betonic. d. 2. myrrhae cina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>momi
d. 1. ſiucci faeniculi d. ſ. fiat maſſa cum aq. faeniculi ac
borago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis. <hi>Take it in ſuch wiſe as is ſhewed in the ſanguine
com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="68" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 68.</hi> For the Chollericke Complexion.</head>
               <p>VVHereas ſome may thinke, that I ſhould haue pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced choller
next vnto blood (according to the order of ſome writers:) firſt becauſe
choller, is the next pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per begotten humour of blood: ſecondly, becauſe
his cell or receptacle, is the neareſt to the blood: thirdly, becauſe it is
of the qualitie of the fyery eleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, which is as they account the worthier
element, beeing the preſeruer, and purger, of moſt things: fourthly,
becauſe it is the beutifulleſt, and the higheſt element in place. Yet
becauſe phlegme is the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginner, and begetter of blood, and blood of
Choller, and melancholie: therefore, I accoumpt it, <hi>prius tempore, &amp;
or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine, ſuſtinendo,</hi> although not <hi>ordine honoris &amp; dignitatis,
in making man:</hi> for when it taketh beeing in the wombe, then are all
humours together in that maſſe or lumpe, or els much of it periſheth, yet
one predominant, <hi>ſecundum ordinem na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae producentis &amp; effectum
coeuntium &amp; planatarum infuſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem:</hi> ſo that none can be ſaid to
be before another, or more vnworthie: becauſe one without the other neither
three without one can make a body neither continue it: therefore I thinke it no
errour.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="69" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 69.</head>
               <p>CHoller exceding in a bodie, giueth to the bodie, deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination
accordingly, and cauſeth the bodie to haue theſe two qualities exceeding
the other, <hi>vz.</hi> hotnes, and dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, whoſe properties are attractiue
to draw vnto it, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this complexion is apt to drawe the infection and
to <pb n="24" facs="tcp:10326:17"/> ioyne with it, becauſe of the hot qualitie in the
ayre naturall, and moyſture naturall, conueighing the vnnaturall heate, and
moyſture into the body, which heate naturall and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall in the ayre, is
entertained of this complexion, not onely for the agreement of the qualitie in
heate, but alſo, for the contrarie qualitie of moyſtnes to drynes, which
would conſume and deſtroy each other, as in fire and water, for euery
qualitie would haue euery ſubſtance to entertaine it, and therefore cold,
heat, moiſtnes and drynes doe infuſe themſelues into ſubſtances: and
heat, cold, moyſtnes and drynes the one contrarie coueteth to depriue the
other: as heat to depriue naturall coldnes, and moyſture naturall dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,
ſo doth vnnaturall heat and moyſtnes, depriue naturall could, and drynes,
as in the peſtilence.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="70" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 70.</head>
               <p>Signes ſhewing this complexion: leane, of meane or lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
ſtature, haire black or darke, moſt commonly curled, eyes quick, colour of
skin ſalow, and in ſome bodies rud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh, voyce ſharpe, vrin high
coloured and cleere, ſharpe or quick, of ſtout courage, ſoone angry,
little ſleepe, dreames of fire, or fighting, pulſe ſwift, and ſtrong,
ſubiect to the gout, eſpecially in the legges, ſubiect to a tertian
feuer, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in warres, liberall in their youth, and midle age, but in ould
age couetous, deſire to trauell, deſirous of venerie, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to
palſie, apoplexies, and trembling.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="71" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 71.</hi> The diet for this complexion.</head>
               <p>Abſtaine from all occaſions which may mooue vnto an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, for
that doth conſume naturall humiditie. Abſtaine from much carnall
copulation, for the exceeding heat doth ſend forth ouermuch humiditie. Faſt
not long, for choller muſt haue to retaine it, or els it conſumeth naturall
moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture. Eate the groſſe meates firſt, (as the phlegmatike muſt
eate the fineſt) becauſe the groſſe will be vndigeſted in the bottome
of the ſtomack, and the fineſt digeſted aboue, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing annoyance by
phlegme, by reaſon of the coldnes of the ſtomacke: ſo in the ſtomacke
of the cholericke, if he eate the fineſt firſt, it will be ſcorched while
the groſſe is dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="72" type="chapter">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:10326:17"/>
               <head>CHAP. 72.</head>
               <p>IF thou beeſt of this complexion, and haue the head hot, vſe
not the flowers of theſe: ſage, melilot, lauender, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonie, chamomill,
roſemarie, the ſweete ruſh, ſquinant, balme, ſcabiones: if thy
breſt be hot, vſe not the flowers of betonie, the ſweete ruſh, balme,
nor ſcabiones: if thy heart be hot, vſe not roſemarie flowers, balme,
ſpikenard, bug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſſe, ſaffron, borrage: if thy ſtomacke be hot, vſe
not the flowers of the ſweete ruſh, ſquinant, roſemarie, neither the
flowers there of: if thy liuer be hot, abſtaine from cento<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, elder buddes,
betonie, chamomill, ſpike, the ſweete ruſh, ſquinant: if thy ſplen be
hot, take heed of the flowers of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonie, and the flowers of the vine, of ripe
grapes: if thy reines be hot or the bladder, vſe not the flowers of melilot,
ſqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, mallowes, ſpike: if the matrix be ouer hot, vſe not the
flowers of betonie, ſquinant, ſage, ſpikenard flower deluce: if the
ioyntes be ouer hot, vſe not the flowers of chamo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mill, melilot, roſemarie
flowers, the primeroſe, or cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſloppe.</p>
               <p>If thy head be ouer hot, abſtaine from theſe hearbs:
ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamint, fennell, bay leaues, margerom, penyriall, ruhe, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorie, and from
the hearbes which beare the flowers before forbidden for the head: if the
breſt be ouer hot vſe not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonie, mayden haire, hyſſope, balme,
horehound, nettle, ſcabions: if the heart be ouer hot, vſe not theſe,
borage, bug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſſe, balme, roſemarie, <hi>Enuſa campana,</hi>
Baſil.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="73" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 73.</head>
               <p>I If thy ſtomack be ouer hot, refraine from theſe hearbes,
woormewod, fennell, mynt, ſage, time If the liuer be hot, refraine from
Egrimonie, fumitorie, hyſop, ſpike margerom, fennell, wormewood, folefoote.
If thy ſplene be ouer hot, abſtaine from calamint, doder, Egrimonie,
creſſes, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly garding creſſes, (for they are hot in the fourth
degree) time, woormewood, hartes tongue. If thy reines be ouer hot abſtaine
from Rocket, fiue leaued graſſe, ſaxifrage, ſpikenard, pellitorie. If
the matrix be ouer hot, abſtaine from mugwoort, calamint, rhue, ſauin,
penyriall: if thy ioynts be ouer hot, abſtaine from chamomil, mleilot,
creſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, <pb n="26" facs="tcp:10326:18"/> rhue, ſage, Egrimonie, S. Iohns woort,
coſtmarie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="74" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 74.</head>
               <p>Vſe theſe ſieldome, galinga, cummin ſeede, aniſe
ſeede, nutmegs, dill, ſmalledge, ſolindine, pepperwoort, ameos,
ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thernwood, muſtard ſeede, garlicke, onyons, rocket, mullin, leekes,
coſtmarie, the roote of gladin, of garden ginger, of doronicke, of radiſh,
of galinga, the roote of water Robin.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="75" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 75.</head>
               <p>Abſtaine from the ruſt of braſſe, the ſcales of
braſſe, burnt braſſe, ſulphur, much ſalt, ſtone ſalt, ſalt
peter, oker, arſinick, the ſpume of the ſea, ſperma caeti, ſweete
amber. Vſe ſieldom cinamon, frankincenſe: abſtaine from burnt wines,
and hot wines. Abſtaine from theſe gummes, the gumme Ammoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acum, the
liquor of the cedar tree, but carefully abſtaine from the gumme
<hi>Euphorbium,</hi> and the gumme <hi>Belzoin.</hi> Of mettalls, theſe you
may better indure then any complexion, the droſſe or ſpume of ſiluer,
quickeſiluer, and the dregges of lead, white lead.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="76" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 76.</head>
               <p>Of ſtones vſe theſe, the chriſtall, the carbuncle, the
rubin, the ſtone ſardin, the granat ſtone: in ſommer the diamant, in
winter the ſaphyre, the Emeraud, the Hyacynth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="77" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 77.</head>
               <p>Of plants, vſe Endiue, cichorie, lettice, plantin, myrrhe,
fleewoort, beetes, ſorrell, knotgraſſe: when heat exceedeth vſe
theſe, hemlocke, poppie, but with direction. Of flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers vſe theſe
commonly, roſes, violets, waterlillies, (and wild poppie with direction:) for
exceſſiue heat, vſe the henbane flowers by direction.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="78" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 78.</head>
               <p>Of fruits vſe theſe, peares, prunes, ſharpe oringes,
lem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, guords, pomegranats, cucumers, myllions, peaches. Of ſeedes vſe
theſe, barly, milion, cichorie, ſorrell. Of rootes mallowes, cichorie,
mandrag. Of woods the cypreſſe, <hi>ſantal. tri. Tamarssk.</hi> Of gummes
Camphure, and the gumme A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabicke.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="79" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 79.</head>
               <p>This will purge all humours in this complexion, but 
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:10326:18"/> moſt properly choller: <hi>R. Rhabarb. dr. 3. ſpic.
Indic. vel cina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>momi dr. 1. Turpet. Polypod. ana dr. 2. Hermodact. dr. 1. fol.
ſenae vn. 1. zingib. ſcr. 2. aniſi ſcr. 1. coquantur in lib. &amp;
ſem. aq. ad ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia partis conſumptionem: &amp; de colatura. dentur vn. 3.
addendo ſyrup. roſarum lax. ſyrup. Endiuiae vel Cichorij vel de ſucco
Endi. ana vn. s.</hi> Take this three mornings or fowre together.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="80" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 80.</head>
               <p>Then within ſeauen or eight daies after, purge your blood with
this, <hi>R. caſſia vn. mellis vn. 1. ſaccar. dr. 2.</hi> infuſe this
in vn. 4. of Endiue water, or cichorie water, and of violet water and borage
water <hi>ana vn.</hi> 2. or in 8 ounces of Endiue or cichorie water.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="81" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 81.</head>
               <p>The water to ſprinkle vpon your clothes, or other places, make
it as for the ſanguine, adding of Cypreſſe vn. <hi>s.</hi> and of
camphure dr. 2. let one halfe be water, the other vineger, adde of the fiue
cold oyles of each vn. s. and led the water be red roſewater which you put
in.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="82" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 82.</head>
               <p>The perfume preſcribed for the ſanguine will ſerue,
ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of <hi>Camphure dr. 2. ſantaiorum trium, Tamariſc, ana dr. 2.</hi>
of roſes, violets, <hi>dr. 2. s.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="83" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 83.</head>
               <p>The bole. <hi>R. bol. Armen. ſiue terrae ſigillat. ſcr. 1.
ſantalorum omnium ſcr. 2.</hi> diſſolue theſe in <hi>aq. violarum
&amp; Endiu. vn. s. vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni albi. vn. s. aq. roſarum vn. 1.</hi> this may you
take at any time, but beſt faſting.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="84" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 84.</head>
               <p>The pills for this complexion; <hi>R. Aloes lotum in aq.
En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diuiae ſiue cichorij, vel in decoctione prunorum damaſc. myrrha dr. 1.
caphur. ſcr. 1. cinamomi dr. 2. cum aqua borag. &amp; Endiu. fiat maſſa
pro pill.</hi> For the vſe hereof looke in the ſanguine com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="85" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 85.</head>
               <p>The pome for this complexion vſe that in the ſanguine compl.
adde <hi>filorum ni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uph. dr.
1. radici cichor. dr. s. cypreſſi dr. 2. cort lemmon. dr.</hi> 1. make it
as before in the ſanguine compl. adding to it in the making, of white lead
dr. s.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="86" type="chapter">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:10326:19"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 86.</hi> The Melancholicke complexion.</head>
               <p>Melancholie naturall, is a humour, whoſe qualities are cold
and drie, of the nature of the earth, the dregs of blood ſetled and ſeuered
from blood (as blood is from phlegme and choller from blood) all which at one
time, were in one cell, the liuer, and by ebullition or concoction, cauſed by
contrarietie of qualities in one ſubſtance and place, to be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered ech
from other to their proper cells: blood to the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer and vaines, choller to
the gall, and melancholie to the ſplene, phlegme to the lungs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="87" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 87.</head>
               <p>This complexion is leaſt apt to take the infection for 3
cauſes: firſt the paſſages are ſtraighter and narrower lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to
the heart, and to the humours about the heart, then in any other complexion.
Secondly by reaſon of the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and the qualities in the ſubſtance, cold
and drines, which are oppoſite vnto the virulent qualitie in the ayre,
exceſſiue heat or moiſture one or both continually reſiſting. Thirdly
in regard of the diſabilitie of the qualities, vnapt to take im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion;
as in cold marble, cold earth, &amp; ſuch like. The ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt times for this
complexion to take it, is when heate and moiſture moſt abound, as in the
ſprings, for then is the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie in the ayre and in the humours moſt
powerfull to alter and ouercome.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="88" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 88.</head>
               <p>Signes ſhewing this complexion, leannes, hardnes of skinne,
colour duskiſh or whitely; pulſe little, haire plaine, ſieldome laughing,
vrine waterie and thinne, excrements ſeege or ſweating, little and
ſtinking: much watchfulnes, yet not ſo much as in the cholerick: dreames
feareful, in opinion ſtiffe, digeſtion ſlow and ill, timerous, long in
anger or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlike if it be begunne, fretting much, ſubiect to one daies
fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, by the vnnaturall heat in the ſpirits of the heart, then is the
colour moſt pale: mooueth ſlowly, ſhortnes or ſtraight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of breath,
heauines of head, and then the vrine is ouer high coloured more then before,
ſome heate is then ouer all the bodie: haire browniſh, and ſometime mixt
with white <pb n="29" facs="tcp:10326:19"/> haires If this humour abound, then are
fearefull dreames, as feare of hurts or harme, death of friends, of pitts and
darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, long feare without cauſe, cramps without repletion, heauines of
mind, ſleepines in the members.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="89" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 89.</head>
               <p>Theſe things are conuenient for this complexion; ſweete
almonds, almond milke, yeolkes of reare egges, milke from the vdder with
ſugar in it, wheat bread. Of ſoules; feſant, henne, capon, field birds.
Of fiſh; roches, dares, gudgines, loches, and ſuch like: veale, yong porke,
redde deere, ſwines ſeete, calues feete, peaſe, pottage with mynt,
figges, raiſons before meate, mynt, rice, lettice, cichorie, grapes, wines
mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deratly and well fined, beare or ale not ouer ſtrong, mirth, braines of
hens, chickins and yong geeſe; it is good to keepe this humour thin.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="90" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 90.</head>
               <p>Theſe are ill, hard meates, drie meates or ſalt, ſower, or
ſcorched meates: colewoorts, muſtard, radiſh, garlicke (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept windines
annoy the bodie) much ſtudie, feare, ſorrow, wrath, compaſſion, care,
much reſt: things grieuous to ſee, to ſmell, or to heare, darknes ill,
drying of the bodie howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, by watching, care, or lecherie: much vſe of
things hot &amp; drie, eſpecially if choller aduſt be in the bodie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="91" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 91.</head>
               <p>Vſe theſe commonly: wormewood, borage, bugloſſe, beetes,
colewoorts, cammomill, Egrimonie, melilot, tinaria, ſpicknard, hearts-tongue,
pellitorie, endiue.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="92" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 92.</head>
               <p>Vſe theſe likewiſe but not ſo commonly, Angelica,
mug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woort, betonie, balme, horehound, myrrhe, roſemarie, ſage, ſeabions,
lupulus, Iuie, peucedanium, water germander, S. Iohns woort, lettice, violets,
arage, beetes: as for other things which are hot in the third or fourth degree,
vſe them with aduiſe, when cold exceedeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="93" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 93.</head>
               <p>VSe theſe commonly: ſweete almondes, iuiubes, the
cypreſſe nut.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="94" type="chapter">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:10326:20"/>
               <head>CHAP. 94.</head>
               <p>THeſe are good to warme the ſplene: bitter almondes,
ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, aniſe ſeede, caraway ſeede, watercreſſes ſeedes,
ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage ſeede, fennell ſeede, gentian, the rootes of penyriall,
gladin.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="95" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 95.</head>
               <p>Things good for the liuer, are likewiſe good for the ſplene,
becauſe the ſplene is hurt from the liuer, and receiueth good from thence:
therefore looke in the ſanguine com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion: things cold or dry in the
ſecond, or third degree, are not commonly to be vſed: and things cold and
dry, in the third degree vtterly to be refuſed, except in the time of
peſtilence, and except they be corrected neuer vſe them in winter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="96" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 96.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THeſe will purge all humours, but eſpecially
melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie:</hi> R. Polypodij dr. 3. fol. ſenae. dr. 11. Turpet. dr. 3.
Rha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barb. hermodact. ana. dr. 1. s. iugib. ſcr. 2. Cinamomi aniſi. ana
ſcr. 1. s. conciſa, coquantur in lib. 1. s. ad tertiae partis
conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem, &amp; de colatura denter. vn. 3. tempore matutino, a den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do
ſyrupi roſarum laxat. ſyrup. fumiter, ana vn. s. <hi>take this three
mornings together, if you doe not ſee by your excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the contrarie, which
ceaſeth to be duskiſh.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="97" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 97.</head>
               <p>Then within ſeauen or eight daies after, take this receipt to
clenſe the blood: <hi>R. Caſſiae mellis ana vn. 1. ſaccar. dr. 3.</hi>
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe theſe in water of fumitorie, vn. 6, or 7. if it be winter in
<hi>aq. Epythimi. vn. 8.</hi> drinke it two mornings together blood-warme.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="98" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 98.</head>
               <p>For the water to ſprinckle vpon your cloaths, or in your
chambers, vſe as before in the ſanguine complex. taking 3. parts water, and
one part vineger: adding to it, of oyle of Chammomill vn. 2. and ſubtracting
as much of the other oyles: if it be in winter, adde oyle of ſpike, dr. 2.
adde vnto it of roſewater, violet water <hi>ana</hi> vn <hi>ſ.</hi> of
balme water, dr. 2. ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract as much out of the other cold waters: adde of
<hi>Traga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent. dr. 1. cedri liq. dr. 2. Thuris dr. 2. ſ.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="99" type="chapter">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:10326:20"/>
               <head>CHAP. 99.</head>
               <p>The ſuffumigation vſe as before in the ſanguine
com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion, adding vnto it of ſpike dr. s. if in winter adde dr. 2. of
frankenſcence, dr. s.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="100" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 100.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>The bole.</hi> R. boli armenij, ſiue terr. figillat.
ſcr. 2. ſantalorum ommium. ſcr. 2. diſſoluantur in aq. roſarum dr.
1. s. aq. meliſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſae violat. ana dr. 2. vini albi dr. 4. mulſi dr. 1.
<hi>the order for making of this is to be obſerued as in the other
complexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="101" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 101.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>The pills. Of</hi> Aloes dr. 2. lot. in vino odoriſer. aq.
violar. aq. meliſſ. ſiue Epythymi ana part. equal. myrrh cinamomi ana dr.
1. fiat maſſa pillularum eum aq. predict. ſit quantitas vt in
preſc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent ſcr. vel. dr. 1.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="102" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 102.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>The pome.</hi> R. ſantalorum odorifer. florum roſarum,
violar, chamomeli ana dr. 1. s. meliſſae dr. 1. cort. citri. dr. 1. s.
macis dr. 2. myrrhae dr. 1. s. camphur. dr. 1. s. ladani dr. 1. papauer ſcr.
s. Ambr. gra. 3. cinamomi gra. 4. nucis moſc. dr. 1 cum Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rebint. lot. in
aq. roſaerum violarum meliſſe, adde ſi poſis de liq. cedri partem
vnam cum aq. predict.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="103" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 103.</head>
               <p>Whereas I haue ſet downe receiptes proper for euery
complexion, as well in purging, and altering the virulent qualitie in the
humours apt to infect, and to be infected, and that in ſuch manner, as the
complexions may be more ſecure then by general receiptes, becauſe you may
properly vſe the ſame, without danger, and offence to any quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in the
hmours naturall, which order euery one cannot ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue, neither is hable:
therefore I haue ſet downe receiptes, reſpecting the good of all: becauſe
they are to purge, and alter the poyſoning qualitie in the ayre, and in all
humors.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="104" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 104.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>The pome.</hi> R. Ambrae, moſchi ana ſcr. s. boli Armen
dr. 6. tadani dr. 3. nucis moſchat. myrrhae, gummi. Iunip. Thur. calami.
odorati, trinus ſantatorum ana ſcr. 1. lig. Aloes, ſtirae. 
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:10326:21"/> chaphurae anae ſcr. 2. ſucci mal. aurantior. ſuc.
portulac. vn. 3. ſem, acetoſae. dr. 3. cornlli rub.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r. s. in aq. roſarum,
&amp; aceto infuſ. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rebent. in aq. roſar. lot. ſyrup. ex cort. mali citri ana quant.
ſufficit, fiat pom.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="105" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 105.</head>
               <p>Another pome. <hi>R. Ladani vn. 1. pulueris cortic. citri
exiccato. vum in vmbra &amp; ſemin. eius ana dr. 1. croci, camphurae, ana dr.
s. roſarum rub. ſcr. 4. cum ſucco ocymi fiat pome.</hi> If you will vſe
this pome in winter, then put vnto it o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> zedoarie dr. 1. ambre ſcr. 1. moſch. ſcr. s. it is good to
hold ſome of this pome in your mouth when you are in a place you ſuſpect,
and to ſmell vnto it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="106" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 106.</head>
               <p>The pilles <hi>R. Aloes vn. s. myrrh, croci ana dr. 2. fiat
maſſa ad pill. foramnd. apta.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take the waight of a dr. s. in the morning, and drinke after it
of wine mixt with water, aſmuch as your mouth will containe at one time: and
before ſupper take ſcr. 1. and drinke as before: let it be white wine in
the morning, and ſacke before ſupper. Vſe this but once a weeke in
ſommer, for ouer often vſe in ſome complexion may cauſe a feuer.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="107" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 107.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Another receipt verie worthie, and neceſſarie, which you
may take as before:</hi> R. corallar. rub. been albi &amp; rub. ana dr. 1.
ſem. catri excorticari, ſem acetoſae ana dr. 1. ſem. gentiana, radic
dictami. Tormentillae ana dr. 2. s. boli Armen. cinamomi electi ana vn. 1.
ſantalorum omnium, ſem ocymi ana ar. 1. s. margaritar. elect. fragmentor.
rubini, ſaphyri hyacinthi ana dr. 1. fiat omnium puluis ſubiliſſimus.
R. de puluere vn. 1. ſacati diſſolut. in aqua roſarum &amp; acetoſ.
fian morſelli.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="108" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 108.</head>
               <p>Take ſometime of the powder, and when you will of the
morſells in the morning or before ſupper: of the powder take dr. s. in the
morning and before ſuper ſcr. 1. drinke the quantitie as in the former
receipt, and let it be with wine one part, and two partes roſewater in the
morning: before ſupper two parts wine, and one parts roſewater: the powder
of this doth ſtay in the paſſages that lead to the heart reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing 
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:10326:21"/> and altering the virulent ayre that is drawne thether: if
you cannot get all the ingredients, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take as many of them as you can, but
leaue not out the bole Armanacke, the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namon, nor the three woods.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="109" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 109.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>The perfume for ſommer.</hi> R. fol. roſarum rub. dr. 1.
myrti camphor. ana vn. s. Thuris dr. 3. cort. citri vn. s. macis dr. 3.
cina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>momi dr. 2. ligni Aloes dr. s. ſantalorum odorif. dr. 3. calamint. dr.
s. Roriſmarini dr. 1.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="110" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 110.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Suffumentum. R. Roſarum rub. vn. s. ligni Aloes dr. 2.
cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorae dr. 3. Thuris dr. 1. macis dr. 3. cinamomi dr. 2. garyophillo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum
dr. 1. cort. citri vn. s. roriſmarini dr. 2. s. myrti dr. 3. ſcin.
Ace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toſae dr. 2. s. ſantalorum omnium dr. 2.</hi> pound theſe and
per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fume with it about the ſetting of the ſunne, and before the ſunne
riſeth, you may vſe the quantitie at your diſcretion: this is moſt
proper for the ſommer time, but if it be in win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then adde theſe, <hi>R.
xiloaloes, coſti dul. ſtorac. ana dr. 3. pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legium, origin. ana dr.
3.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="111" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 111.</head>
               <p>The water. Vſe this in ſommer, <hi>R. cort. granat.
citonior. &amp; Gbanae ana vn. 1. Alchechengi, Tamariſci, coriandri, Ribes
ana. vn. s. nenifar. vn. 1. fol. roſarum rub. violar. ma. s. myrti p. 1.
portulacae, plantaginis, fol. ſalui, chamomillae ana ma. 1.</hi> boyle
theſe in two pints of vineger, and one pint of water, &amp; adde vnto it, of
oyle of chamomil, of water lillies, of violets, of ech halfe an ounce: vſe it
as before in the complexions. When you vſe it, put in of this infuſion made
as followeth, <hi>R. ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur. dr. 1. ſantalor. omnium, Thuris, gummi Iunip
ana dr. s. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fundantur in vn. 1. aceti vn. 2. aq. roſarum hor. 8. fortiter
expri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menter.</hi> In winter, adde of theſe; <hi>R. Ambrae dr. s. coſti
dulc. dr. 1. ſtorac. dr. s. cypreſſi dr. 1. origani, pulegij. fol lanc.
ana m. s.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="112" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 112.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A receipt to clenſe the blood in any complexion.</hi> R.
Caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae, mellis ana vn. 1. diaprun. non ſolut. dr. 3. s. fundantur in
aqua Endiuiae, ſiue cichorij vn. 3. vini alb. vn. 2. leniter expriment. fiat
pot. pro motutinis duob. vel. trib.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="113" type="chapter">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:10326:22"/>
               <head>CHAP. 113.</head>
               <p>Signes ſhewing the heart or humours about the heart, to be
infected with the peſtilent feuer, by the hot qualitie in the ayre.</p>
               <p>A vehement heat within, and without little or none: and if it be
confirmed, the breath ſtinketh more then it was woont by much: pulſe, vrin,
and digeſtion, doe ſeldome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare it. There is heat of the breath,
diſquiet, and ſtraightnes of breath, the breaſt is felt to be narrower,
and the breath is reſtrained, thirſtines, drines of tongue, blacknes of
tongue, with puſtulls or bliſters vpon the lippes and tongue: trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling of
the heart and pulſe: the breath goeth ſhort: and there is ſometime a
ſounding, making the outward parts cold: ſometime a drie cough, ſomtime
there appeare ſores, of colour whitiſh, blew, and redde: the digeſtion is
thin, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid, ſpumie, ſtinking, and vnctuous: ſome doe vomit, ſome
haue the fluxe, the vrin is ſtinking.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="114" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 114.</head>
               <p>If the heart be poſſeſſed principally, with extreme
heate from the ayre, then the bodie is commonly hot, except the liuer preuent
it, the pulſe is ſwift in motion, much puffing or blowing, by reaſon the
heart mooueth ſo ſwiftly in this paſſion: the bodie commonly is
fooliſh, and bold: this qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie killeth ſooneſt, becauſe it mooueth
with the ſpirits vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, and animall, moſt ſpeedily.</p>
               <p>If the heart be infected with the virulent qualities of heat,
and moiſture, then the pulſe mooueth ſlower, likewiſe the breath. This
deſtroieth ſlower. And if there be equalitie of the qualities, then the
bodie lingereth, and is long dying, or els ſoares commonly, ſaue.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="115" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 115.</head>
               <p>Meanes to know who is infected with the peſtilence. Take
bole-Armoniack dr. 1. of white wine vn. 1. of roſewa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vn. 2. mixt theſe:
take it faſting, (and fitting halfe an houre after) or before ſupper: if
the bodie vomit, it is infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted. And for further proofe of this, (let the
partie that vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miteth vpon the receipt,) breathe into the mouth of a cock, and
if the cock languiſh or die within twelue houres, then it <pb n="35" facs="tcp:10326:22"/> is greatly to be feared that the bodie is infected.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="116" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 116.</head>
               <p>A meanes to know if any roomes be infected, and by the ſame,
and the generall perfume next before, to purge and clenſe the roomes: put two
or three ſheepe into the roomes, three or foure daies before the full or
change: and there continue them, vntill the next full or change: and then
waſh them, or one of them, in warme water: and put the water to waſh or
ſwill, or mixt, ſo as ſwine may drinke it: and if the ſwine doe die,
the infection is moſt part taken out of the houſe: then perfume the houſe
as before.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="117" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 117.</head>
               <p>If two, or moe lie ſicke of the peſtilence, and no ſoare
ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare; by this receipt following you may perceiue which will liue.</p>
               <p>Take of bole-Armoniack, white wine, and roſewater, the
quantitie before mentioned, and adde vnto it, of ſaffron ſcr. 1. finely
pounded, of methridate ſcr. 2. and take it in manner aforeſaid, and which
of them vomit is like to die, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are like to liue: this I lately
prooued at <hi>Weſſon</hi> by Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thampton, as the parents of two children
can teſtifie, to whome I tolde, that the bodie that did vomit, was in great
danger to die, and the other was in hope to liue: which came ſo to paſſe,
and ſhee which liued had a ſoare.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="118" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 118.</head>
               <p>Whereas they doe moſt infect, which haue ſores, the aire,
and clothes continually receiuing the virulent matter, and qualities from them;
and the bodie moſt commonly able to walke into companies, and that without
ſuſpition: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, by theſe meanes following they may be found
out.</p>
               <p>If you ſuſpect any, as you may iuſtly, whhere ſome haue
died out of a houſe, or where the next houſe haue had the infection, then
doe as followeth; Command them to ſtand vpright, and to reatch themſelues
vpright: if they faile to doe it, then ſuſpect a ſore in the backe,
bellie, breſt, or flanks: after that, preſently command them, to lay their
hands vpon a dore, or beame; if they hang more by one arme then by the other,
or their neckes hang awrie, ſuſpect a ſoare vnder <pb n="36" facs="tcp:10326:23"/>
the arme, vpon the arme ſhoulders, or in the necke: preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after this,
command them to walke vp and downe as faſt as they can; if they halt, or
ſteppe not largely, ſuſpect a ſore in the thighs, flanks, knees, backe,
or hyppes: preſently after this, command them to bow down foreward to the
ground, and reach vp ſomething, not remoouing any foote, if they cannot, then
ſuſpect the flanks, or backe: if they doe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme all this, and be very
ſhort winded, hauing no other diſeaſe knowne; then ſuſpect a ſoare
to enſue, or the bodie very ſhortly to be in great danger by the
peſtilence.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="119" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 119.</head>
               <p>A breife order for thoſe, which are ſhut vp, and not hable
to vſe the meanes before ſet downe: let them which are cleare in the
houſe, doe as followeth: ſleepe little, for ſo thy bodie ſhalbe made
more dry, rub thy thighes, and armes, morning and euening, and if you can
againſt the fire, ſo ſhall the humours about the heart with the blood, be
out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, apt to be ſwet out at the emunctorie places. Let thy bread haue the
third part barly, which is cooling and dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, let thy drinke be for the
moſt part, (eſpecially in the end of dinner and ſupper) of a ptiſme
made with barlie, as followeth:</p>
            </div>
            <div n="120" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 120.</head>
               <p>Take a pynt of barly, and 4. pyntes of running water, beate the
barly vntill the huske depart, then when you haue winnowed it, put it into the
water, and there let it continue, vntill it beginne to boyle, then take the
barly from the water, and put it into a veſſell wherein is eight pintes of
water rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to boyle, or very hot: let it boyle vntill you thinke that two or
three pyntes be waſted, then ſtrayne it, and afer it be cold, keepe it in a
ſtone bottle or pot; and when you drinke of it, put into your draught, if it
be halfe a pynt, a ſpoonfull or ſome deale leſſe of vineger: and if you
be coſſiue, put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it of ſugar halfe a quarter of an ounce or a little
more, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it ſo as it be neither ouer ſharpe, nor ouer ſweet, and if
you infuſe all night an ounce of Tamarandes in halfe a pynt of your ptiſme,
and drinke it faſting, it is very good.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="121" type="chapter">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:10326:23"/>
               <head>CHAP. 121.</head>
               <p>Vſe vineger with your meates, vſe the pills of aloes
men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned before: when you make your beddes, and in the morning when you
riſe, ſmell to a ſponge, or cloth dipped in vineger: keepe no water in
the houſe long, neither ſuffer wett places in the houſe, for moyſture
will putrifie by the virulent ayre, where the ſunne or fyre commeth not: eate
no hearbes, or very few, neither haue them in your houſe, walke not early, or
late in the ayre, lye not on the ſide of the houſe, where the ſunne
ſhineth moſt; (although the ſunne be a meanes to purge the ayre) for that
draweth the infection to the roome, and heateth the place, which if it
retaineth any that is not exhaled or altered, then it is apt to infect,
remayning in the ayre in the roomes, after the depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the ſunne and
not in other ſolid matters, as bodies, clothes, or ſuch like, to the which
the ayre will conueigh it in the night more ſpeedily after the departure of
the ſunne.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="122" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 122.</head>
               <p>Foraſmuch as I haue ſpent more time about preſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues,
then about the cure: my reaſon is, becauſe no man can doe that certainely,
except he ſee the paſſions, aſwell to know whether it be in the way to
be confirmed at the heart, or whether it be confirmed: and then no cure.
Secondly in ſome bodies complexion, feare, greife, or other infirmities,
cauſe it to be more ſharpe, and ſtrange at one time, then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, and
in one bodie more then another. Thirdly, the epidemiall or peſtilent feuer,
neuer ceaſeth to make impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, to corrupt, and poyſon, becauſe
the body is apt and diſpoſed to take it, but in what quantitie the abſent
phiſition cannot certainly tell, therefore no certaine cure: the ſecureſt
way is, to haue the phyſition preſent or not farre from thee, who may vſe
meanes accordingly: for ſo long as it is in the way to be confirmed, ſo
long is there hope, by things which exceede the impreſſion, and may make
the bodie more vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>apt to intertaine and keepe it: and laſtly rectifie and
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme what is decaied.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:10326:24"/>HEre inſueth a table collected out of
Pythagoras, with certaine breife notes added therevnto, whereby may be knowne
in all humorall diſeaſes (without ſight of vrin or patient) what part of
the body is ill affected, what humor aboundeth, &amp; cauſeth the
paſſion. Which beeing knowne, you may looke into the diſcourſe of the
complexion, there ſhall you find what is to correct the offending humours,
and to purge the peccant matter: what diet is to be vſed, and what hurtfull
things are to be auoided. For the finding out of the cauſe, and the affected
place: you are to inquire what day the bodie did firſt feele any paſſion
or greife, then looke for the planet that ruleth that day, (as <hi>Saturne</hi>
accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the greekes) beginneth to raignne betweene xij. and 1. of the
clock in Sondaies night, and continueth vntill xij. of the clock in Saturdaies
night. <hi>Iupiter</hi> beginneth to raigne at xij. of the clock in Frydayes
night, and raigneth vntill xij. of the clock in Thurſdaies night. So
likewiſe is <hi>Mars</hi> for Tueſdaye, <hi>Sol</hi> for Sonday,
<hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enus</hi> for Friday, <hi>Mercurie</hi> for wedenſday, and
<hi>Luna</hi> for monday. Looke in the Alma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nack in what ſigne <hi>Sol</hi>
is in that moneth wherein the patient fel ſick, then in what ſigne the
moone is that day wherein he fell ſick: this being done, looke in the
higheſt columne of the day for the planit wherein he felt his paſſion
firſt: then look in the firſt columne for the ſigne the ſunne is in in
that moneth, and for the ſigne the moone was in that day when he firſt fell
ſick, and againſt the ſignes, in the columne right vnder the planet of
the daie, ſhall you ſee the places ill af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected. As for example, one
falleth ſicke vpon a humorall diſeaſe, the 21. day of May beeing mondaie
in the yeare of our Lord 1604. the ſunne beeing in Gemini, the Moone in
Cancer, Luna beeing the planet of that day: now in the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumne right vnder
Luna, and againſt Gemini, may you ſee armes ill affected. In the columne
right vnder Luna, againſt Cancer, may you ſee head and ſtomacke ill
affected. In the page following may you ſee Luna, and vnder that ſhall you
read the cauſe, with the affected places.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:10326:24"/> 
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label"> </cell>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>Luna</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>Mercurie</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>
                              <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enus</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>Sol</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>Mars</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>Iupiter</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>Saturnus</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ries</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Head knees</cell>
                        <cell>Legs co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of skin and calfe.</cell>
                        <cell>Feete</cell>
                        <cell>Loynes</cell>
                        <cell>Head</cell>
                        <cell>Bellie</cell>
                        <cell>Breaſt</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>urus</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Necke ſhin bone</cell>
                        <cell>Feete</cell>
                        <cell>Head</cell>
                        <cell>Knees</cell>
                        <cell>Necke</cell>
                        <cell>Backe</cell>
                        <cell>Bellie</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                                 <desc>•••</desc>
                              </gap>in.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Armes</cell>
                        <cell>Head</cell>
                        <cell>Necke</cell>
                        <cell>Legges</cell>
                        <cell>Breaſt</cell>
                        <cell>Priuities</cell>
                        <cell>Bellie</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                                 <desc>•••</desc>
                              </gap>cer</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Head Stomack</cell>
                        <cell>Eyes Necke</cell>
                        <cell>Armes Legges</cell>
                        <cell>Feete</cell>
                        <cell>Breaſt</cell>
                        <cell>Loynes</cell>
                        <cell>Priuities</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>o</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Necke Stomack</cell>
                        <cell>Necke Armes</cell>
                        <cell>Heart</cell>
                        <cell>Head</cell>
                        <cell>Bellie</cell>
                        <cell>Knees</cell>
                        <cell>Priuities</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>irgo</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Armes</cell>
                        <cell>Heart</cell>
                        <cell>Bellie Stomack</cell>
                        <cell>Necke</cell>
                        <cell>Bellie</cell>
                        <cell>Knees</cell>
                        <cell>Feete</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>bra</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Heart Loynes</cell>
                        <cell>Bellie</cell>
                        <cell>Head Bellie</cell>
                        <cell>Armes</cell>
                        <cell>Priuities</cell>
                        <cell>Head Eyes</cell>
                        <cell>Knees</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="4 letters">
                                 <desc>••••</desc>
                              </gap>pio</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Bellie Feete</cell>
                        <cell>Backe</cell>
                        <cell>Feete</cell>
                        <cell>Heart</cell>
                        <cell>Head Armes</cell>
                        <cell>Feete</cell>
                        <cell>Feete</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="4 letters">
                              <desc>••••</desc>
                           </gap>t.</cell>
                        <cell>Backe</cell>
                        <cell>Head Priuities</cell>
                        <cell>Armes Priuities</cell>
                        <cell>Backe</cell>
                        <cell>Hands Feete</cell>
                        <cell>Legges head</cell>
                        <cell>Feete</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="4 letters">
                                 <desc>••••</desc>
                              </gap>ic.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Loynes Knees</cell>
                        <cell>Priuities</cell>
                        <cell>Heart Loynes</cell>
                        <cell>Shinne-bone.</cell>
                        <cell>Armes Legges</cell>
                        <cell>Eyes Knees</cell>
                        <cell>head Bellie</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="4 letters">
                              <desc>••••</desc>
                           </gap>r.</cell>
                        <cell>Priuities Feete</cell>
                        <cell>Heart Loynes</cell>
                        <cell>Knees</cell>
                        <cell>Priuities</cell>
                        <cell>Heart</cell>
                        <cell>Armes heart</cell>
                        <cell>head Necke</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="5 letters">
                              <desc>•••••</desc>
                           </gap>s.</cell>
                        <cell>Feete Priuities</cell>
                        <cell>Legges Priuities</cell>
                        <cell>Necke Backe</cell>
                        <cell>Loynes</cell>
                        <cell>Bellie</cell>
                        <cell>head heart</cell>
                        <cell>Necke Armes</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <div n="Sunday" type="diagnosis">
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:10326:25"/>
                  <head>Sol</head>
                  <p>Yeallow choller aboundeth, payne at the heart and raines
moſt, all the members are greiued: the bodie exceeding hot, little or no
ſleepe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Monday" type="diagnosis">
                  <head>Lunae</head>
                  <p>The head infected with phlegmatick humors, payne in the
loynes, payne in the right ſide and in the lunges, dull and ſleepie, the
cauſe cold and moyſtnes, great danger.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Tuesday" type="diagnosis">
                  <head>Mars</head>
                  <p>Heate in the raines, head, lightes, &amp; the kings euill to
be fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: the cauſe yeallow choller, beginning to be aduſted cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
hotnes and drynes.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Wednesday" type="diagnosis">
                  <head>Mercurie</head>
                  <p>Lunges greiued, breath drawne ſhort with paine, the bodie
and ſences troubled, ſwelling in the bodie, paine in the loynes: the
cauſe of great heat taking cold.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Thursday" type="diagnosis">
                  <head>Iupiter</head>
                  <p>Great heat in the liuer, and vnder the lightes about the right
ſide, he hath the feuer Synocham: the cauſe is putrifaction of blood, by
exceſſe of blood and diſtemperature in the ſame.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Friday" type="diagnosis">
                  <head>Venus</head>
                  <p>The liuer, Raines, ſtones, backbone payned, and vnder the
bellie greife: the cauſe cold and moyſtnes, but moſt cold if it be a man,
otherwiſe cold and moyſtnes together in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſexe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Saturday" type="diagnosis">
                  <head>Saturne</head>
                  <p>The ſtomack, loines, and ſplene ill: the firſt
paſſion felt in the ſplene: if it continue 8. daies all the bodie will be
likewiſe greiued: the cauſe told and drynes, begun in the ſplene, and
like to continue long.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:10326:25"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
